Guide to the Miriam Hapgood DeWitt Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce Correspondence, 1857-1954; Series III; 5.52; (13.5 boxes)
  The second subseries holds the bulk of the DeWitt papers collection, a set of chronologically arranged letters written among Hapgood family members, and between Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce and their circle of friends. Miriam Hapgood DeWitt and her sister Beatrix Hapgood Faust collected the material from libraries around the country, including the Beinecke Library; correspondence related to their efforts can be found in Series I.
  While assembling the collection, the sisters created typed transcriptions of most of the letters, and attempted to assign dates to undated items. In some cases, the sisters were able to give fairly specific dates but in others, they could only approximate a year or time of a year (i.e., "early spring 1916"). At the beginning of the files for many of the years there are folders containing letters to which they assigned approximate dates. Three folders of undated letters and fragments are filed at the end of the subseries; many of these items may be second copies of letters that also appear somewhere within the chronological set.
  In addition to the photocopies of letters they acquired from institutions, the sisters gathered family correspondence from their own homes and relatives, and interfiled these original manuscript letters with the photocopies and transcripts. Many are from Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce to their children, and from the children to their parents; as such, the incidence of original letters increases as the years progress. There are also original letters from the Hapgoods' colleagues and friends; some examples are an otherwise undated 1938 letter from Pauline Hemingway to Neith Boyce, an eight-page letter from Mabel Dodge Luhan to Hutchins Hapgood written from a Taos hospital in September 1942, and two folders of condolence letters received by Boyce after the death of Hutchins Hapgood in November 1944.
  As the sisters had intended, the collection of letters provides a good chronological narrative of the lives, activities, and thoughts of Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce. In addition, it sheds light on the dynamic of their highly creative community, such as in the colorful commentary on the Taos, New Mexico, scene sent back East in several letters by Neith Boyce and Miriam DeWitt while they were visiting Mabel Dodge Luhan during the summer and fall of 1929.
  When using this part of the DeWitt papers, readers may find it helpful to refer to the list of nicknames used within the Hapgood family, which appears as an addendum to the library's Hapgood Family Papers (YCAL MSS 41).
  - "The Undiscover'd Country"
    - Book proposal, undated (Box 10, Folder 133-134)
    - List of [Harry] Boyce's letters, undated (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Letters collection
    Letters with dates narrowed to a month (i.e., "April 1916") are filed at the beginning of the month. Those with span dates (i.e., "April-May 1916" or "1916-1917") are filed where the date range starts. In all cases, if there are typed transcripts, they precede the copies of the manuscript letters.
    - Letters, 1857-1900 (Box 10, Folder 136-150)
    - Letters, 1901-1907 (Box 11, Folder 151-166)
    - Letters, 1908-1914 (Box 12, Folder 167-181)
    - Letters, 1915-1917 (Box 13, Folder 182-194)
    - Letters, 1918-1919 (Box 14, Folder 195-207)
    - Letters, 1920-1923 (Box 15, Folder 208-225)
    - Letters, 1924-1927 (Box 16, Folder 226-239)
    - Letters, 1928-1929 (Box 17, Folder 240-250)
    - Letters, 1930-1931 (Box 18, Folder 251-262)
    - Letters, 1932-1935 (Box 19, Folder 263-277)
    - Letters, 1936-1938 (Box 20, Folder 278-291)
    - Letters, 1939-1941 (Box 21, Folder 292-306)
    - Letters, 1942-1954 (Box 22, Folder 307-321)
    - Letter excerpts (transcript), undated (Box 23, Folder 322)
    - Letters, undated (Box 23, Folder 323-325)
- Hapgood Circle Writings, 1911-1932; Series IV; 0.11; (.5 box)
  Organized in alphabetical order by author
  The series primarily contains photocopies of newspaper columns, essays, and articles written by the Hapgoods' colleagues, and collected by Miriam Hapgood DeWitt. There are a few contemporary clippings, typescripts, and published versions in the files. Photocopies are distinguished in the folder listing, but the dates shown are those of the original materials regardless if they are photocopies or originals.
  Similar material by Hutchins Hapgood and Neith Boyce is filed in the Writings subseries of Series II, Hapgood Family Papers.
  - Aisen, Maurice, "The Latest Evolution in Art and Picabia," printed version photocopy, 1913 Jun (Box 23, Folder 326)
  - Cook, George Cram, "Change Your Style," computer printout of 1915 script, photocopy, undated (Box 23, Folder 327)
  - Haywood, William D., The General Strike, 2nd edition, printed version, 1911 (Box 23, Folder 328)
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, essays, printed versions and photocopies, 1932, undated (Box 23, Folder 329)
    Includes "Decline of the Male," "The Mirror," and "Speculations"
  - Stein, Gertrude, essays from Camera Work, printed version photocopies, 1912-1913 (Box 23, Folder 330)
    Includes "Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia," "Pablo Picasso," and "Henri Matisse"
  - Van Vechten, Carl, "Once Aboard the Lugger, San Guglielmo," printed version photocopy, 1914 Oct (Box 23, Folder 331)
  - Wyneken, Gustav, Eros, printed version, 1922 (Box 23, Folder 332)
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  - DeWitt, Miriam, and John (in Series I), 1972 Mar 23 (Box 24, Folder 333)
  - Labor, unions, and strikes (in Series I), 1977-1988 (Box 24, Folder 334)
  - Provincetown, Massachusetts (in Series I), undated (Box 24, Folder 335)
  - Writers and writing (in Series I), 1950-1988 (Box 24, Folder 336)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (in Series I), 1974-1986 (Box 24, Folder 337)
  - Hapgood, Hutchins, ephemera (in Series II), 1939 (Box 24, Folder 338)
  - Miscellaneous ephemera (in Series II), 1910-1935, undated (Box 24, Folder 339)
- Restricted Fragile
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 8, folder 111 (Box 25, Folder 340)